<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="implementing" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<title>Implementing Service Providers</title>
	<para>
		The spring-social-core module provides support for implementing your own ServiceProviders.
		This support consists of convenient base classes for the various ServiceProvider types, such as OAuth1 and OAuth2-based providers.
		In this section, you will learn how to implement ServiceProviders.
	</para>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing-oauth2">
		<title>OAuth2 Service Providers</title>
		<para>
			To implement an OAuth2-based ServiceProvider, first extend AbstractOAuth2ServiceProvider.
			Parameterize &lt;S&gt; to be the Java Binding to the ServiceProvider API.
			Define a single constructor that accepts an clientId and clientSecret,
			Finally, implement getServiceApi(String) to return a new API instance.
		</para>
		<para>
			See FacebookServiceProvider as an example of an OAuth2-based ServiceProvider:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public final class FacebookServiceProvider extends AbstractOAuth2ServiceProvider<FacebookApi> {

    public FacebookServiceProvider(String clientId, String clientSecret) {
        super(new OAuth2Template(clientId, clientSecret,
            "https://graph.facebook.com/oauth/authorize", 
            "https://graph.facebook.com/oauth/access_token"));
    }

    public FacebookApi getServiceApi(String accessToken) {
        return new FacebookTemplate(accessToken);
    }

}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			In the constructor, you should call super, passing up the configured OAuth2Template, which implements OAuth2Operations.
			The OAuth2Template will handle the "OAuth dance" with the provider, and should be configured with the provided clientId and clientSecret, along with the provider-specific authorizeUrl and accessTokenUrl.
		</para>
		<para>
			In getServiceApi(String), you should construct your Service API implementation, passing it the access token needed to make requests for protected resources.
			Inside the API implementation, we generally recommend using RestTemplate to make the HTTP calls and add the required Authorization header:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public FacebookTemplate(String accessToken) {
    // creates a RestTemplate that adds the OAuth2-draft10 Authorization header to each request before it is executed
    restTemplate = ProtectedResourceClientFactory.draft10(accessToken);
}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			An example API call with RestTemplate is shown below:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public FacebookProfile getUserProfile(String facebookId) {
    return new FacebookProfile(restTemplate.getForObject("https://graph.facebook.com/{facebookId}", Map.class, facebookId));
}]]>
		</programlisting>
	</section>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing-oauth1">
		<title>OAuth1 Service Providers</title>
		<para>
			To implement an OAuth1-based ServiceProvider, first extend AbstractOAuth1ServiceProvider.
			Parameterize &lt;S&gt; to be the Java Binding to the ServiceProvider API.
			Define a single constructor that accepts a consumerKey and consumerSecret.
			Finally, implement getServiceApi(String, String) to return a new API instance.
		</para>
		<para>
			See TwitterServiceProvider as an example of an OAuth1-based ServiceProvider:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public final class TwitterServiceProvider extends AbstractOAuth1ServiceProvider<TwitterApi> {

    public TwitterServiceProvider(String consumerKey, String consumerSecret) {
        super(consumerKey, consumerSecret,  new OAuth1Template(consumerKey, consumerSecret, 
                "https://twitter.com/oauth/request_token",
                "https://twitter.com/oauth/authorize",
                "https://twitter.com/oauth/access_token"));
    }

    public TwitterApi getServiceApi(String accessToken, String secret) {
        return new TwitterTemplate(getConsumerKey(), getConsumerSecret(), accessToken, secret);
    }

}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			In the constructor, you should call super, passing up the the consumerKey, secret, and configured OAuth1Template.
			The OAuth1Template will handle the "OAuth dance" with the provider.
			It should be configured with the provided consumerKey and consumerSecret, along with the provider-specific requestTokenUrl, authorizeUrl, and accessTokenUrl.
		</para>			
		<para>
			In getServiceApi(String, String), you should construct your Service API implementation, passing it the four tokens needed to make requests for protected resources.
			Inside the API implementation, we generally recommend using RestTemplate to make the HTTP calls and add the required Authorization header:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterTemplate(String consumerKey, String consumerSecret, String accessToken, String accessTokenSecret) {
    // creates a RestTemplate that adds the OAuth1 Authorization header to each request before it is executed
    restTemplate = ProtectedResourceClientFactory.create(consumerKey, consumerSecret, accessToken, accessTokenSecret);
}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			An example API call with RestTemplate is shown below:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterProfile getUserProfile(String screenName) {
    return new TwitterProfile(restTemplate.getForObject("https://api.twitter.com/1/users/show.json?screen_name={screenName}", Map.class, screenName));
}]]>
		</programlisting>									
	</section>
</chapter>