<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="implementing" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<title>Adding Support for a New Service Provider</title>
	<para>
		Spring Social makes it easy to add support for service providers that are not already supported by the framework.
		If you review the existing client modules, such as spring-social-twitter and spring-social-facebook, you will discover they are implemented in a consistent manner and they apply a set of well-defined extension points.
		In this section, you will learn how to add support for new service providers you wish to integrate into your applications.
	</para>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing">
		<title>Process</title>
		<para>
			The process of adding client support for a service provider consists of several steps:
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Create a source project for the client code e.g. <code>spring-social-twitter</code>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Develop or integrate a Java binding to the provider's "Service API" e.g. <code>TwitterApi</code>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Create a ServiceProvider implementation that allows users to authorize with the provider and obtain Service API instances e.g. <code>TwitterServiceProvider</code>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Create a ServiceApiAdapter that maps the provider's native Service API onto the uniform ServiceProviderConnection model e.g. <code>TwitterServiceApiAdapter</code>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Finally, create a ServiceProviderConnectionFactory that wraps the other artifacts up and provides a simple interface for establishing connections e.g. <code>TwitterServiceProviderConnectionFactory</code></para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			The following sections of this chapter walk you through each of the steps with examples.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing-project">
		<title>Creating a source project for the provider client code</title>
		<para>
			A Spring Social client module is simply a standard Java project that builds a jar artifact e.g. spring-social-twitter.jar.
			We do recommend the actual code structure follow several packaging guidelines described below.
			To make this as easy as possible to do, we have also created a template project you may use as a starting point.
		</para>
		<section id="service-providers-implementing-project-structure">
			<title>Code structure recommendations</title>
			<para>
				We recommend all code for a new Spring Social client module fall within the <code>org.springframework.social.{providerId}</code> base package,
				where {providerId} is a unique identifier you assign to the service provider you are adding support for.
				Consider some of the providers already supported by the framework as examples:
				<table xml:id="service-providers-implementing-project-structure-examples">
					<title>Spring Social Client Projects</title>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						<colspec align="left" />
						<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2*" />
						<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*" />
						<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="2*" />
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry align="center">Provider ID</entry>
								<entry align="center">Artifact Name</entry>
								<entry align="center">Base Package</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>facebook</entry>
								<entry>spring-social-facebook</entry>
								<entry>org.springframework.social.facebook</entry>
							</row>					
							<row>
								<entry>twitter</entry>
								<entry>spring-social-twitter</entry>
								<entry>org.springframework.social.twitter</entry>
							</row>					
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>
			<para>
				Within the base package, we recommend the following subpackage structure:
				<table>
					<title>Module Structure</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<colspec align="left" />
						<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2*" />
						<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*" />
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry align="center">Subpackage</entry>
								<entry align="center">Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>api</entry>
								<entry>The public interface of the Java API binding.</entry>
							</row>					
							<row>
								<entry>api.impl</entry>
								<entry>The primary implementation of the Java API binding.</entry>
							</row>					
							<row>
								<entry>connect</entry>
								<entry>The types necessary to establish connections to the service provider.</entry>
							</row>					
						</tbody>					
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>
			<para>
				You can see this recommended structure in action by reviewing one of the other client modules such as spring-social-twitter:`
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject role="fo">
						<imagedata fileref="images/spring-social-twitter-example.png" format="PNG" align="center" />
					</imageobject>
					<imageobject role="html">
						<imagedata fileref="images/spring-social-twitter-example.png" format="PNG" align="center" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</para>
			<para>
				Here, the central service API type, TwitterApi, is located in the api package along with its supporting operations types and data transfer object types.
				The primary implementation of that interface, TwitterTemplate, is located in the api.impl package (along with other package-private impl types have that been excluded from this view).
				Finally, the connect package contains the implementations of various connect SPIs that enable connections to Twitter to be established and persisted.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing-api">
		<title>Developing a Java binding to the provider's API</title>
		<para>
			Spring Social favors the development of strongly-typed Java bindings to external service provider APIs.
			This provides a simple, domain-oriented interface for Java applications to use to consume the API.
			When adding support for a new service provider, if no suitable Java binding already exists you'll need to develop one.
			If one already exists, such as Twitter4j for example, it is possible to integrate it into the framework. 
		</para>
		<section id="service-provider-implementing-api-new-designing">
			<title>Designing a new Java API binding</title>
			<para>
				API developers retain full control over the design and implementation of their Java bindings.
				That said, we offer several design guidelines in an effort to improve overall consistency and quality:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Favor separating the API binding interface from the implementation.</emphasis>
							This is illustrated in the spring-social-twitter example in the previous section.
							There, "TwitterApi" is the central API binding type and it is declared in the org.springframework.social.twitter.api package with other public types.
							"TwitterTemplate" is the primary implementation of this interface and is located in the org.springframework.social.twitter.api.impl subpackage along with other package-private implementation types.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis>Favor organizing the API binding hierarchically by RESTful resource.</emphasis>
							REST-based APIs typically expose access to a number of resources in an hierarchical manner.
							For example, Twitter's API provides access to "status timelines", "searches", "lists", "direct messages", "friends", and "users".
							Rather than add all operations across these resources to a single flat "TwitterApi" interface, the TwitterApi interface is organized hierarchically:
							<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public interface TwitterApi {
	
    DirectMessageOperations directMessageOperations();

    FriendOperations friendOperations();

    ListOperations listOperations();

    SearchOperations searchOperations();
	
    TimelineOperations timelineOperations();

    UserOperations userOperations();

}]]></programlisting>
						</para>
						<para>
							DirectMessageOperations, for example, contains API bindings to Twitter's "direct_messages" resource:
							<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public interface DirectMessageOperations {

    List<DirectMessage> getDirectMessagesReceived();

    List<DirectMessage> getDirectMessagesSent();

    void sendDirectMessage(String toScreenName, String text);

    void sendDirectMessage(long toUserId, String text);
	
    void deleteDirectMessage(long messageId);
}]]>
							</programlisting>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="service-provider-implementing-api-new-implementing">
			<title>Implementing a new Java API binding</title>
			<para>
				API developers are free to implement their Java API binding with whatever HTTP/REST client they see fit.
				That said, Spring Social's existing API bindings such as spring-social-twitter all use Spring Framework's RestTemplate in conjunction with the Jackson JSON ObjectMapper.
				RestTemplate is a popular REST client that provides a uniform object mapping interface across a variety of data exchange formats (JSON, XML, etc).
				Jackson is the leading Java-based JSON marshalling technology.
				To help promote consistency across Spring Social's supported bindings, we do recommend you consider these implementation technologies (and please let us know if they do not meet your needs).
			</para>
			<para>
				Spring Social has adopted a convention where each API implementation class is named "{ProviderId}Template" e.g. TwitterTemplate.
				We favor this convention unless there is a good reason to deviate from it.
				As discussed in the previous section, we also recommend keeping implementation types separate from the public API types.
				And we recommend keeping internal implementation details package-private.
			</para>
			<para>
				The way in which an API binding implementation is constructed will vary based on the API's authorization protocol.
				For APIs secured with OAuth1, the consumerKey, consumerSecret, accessToken, and accessTokenSecret will be required for construction:
				<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterTemplate(String consumerKey, String consumerSecret, String accessToken, String accessTokenSecret) { ... }]]>
				</programlisting>				
			</para>
			<para>
				For OAuth2, only the access token should be required:
				<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public FacebookTemplate(String accessToken) { ... }]]>
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				Each request made to the API's "resource server" needs to be signed with the OAuth credentials provided during construction.
				This signing process consists of adding an "Authorization" header to each client request before it is executed.
				For OAuth1, the process is quite complicated, and is used to support an elaborate request signature verification algorithm between the client and server.
				For OAuth2, it is a lot simpler, but does still vary across the various drafts of the OAuth2 specification.
			</para>
			<para>
				To encapsulate this complexity, for each authorization protocol Spring Social provides a ProtectedResourceClientFactory you may use to
				construct a pre-configured RestTemplate instance that performs the request signing for you. For OAuth1:
				<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterTemplate(String consumerKey, String consumerSecret, String accessToken, String accessTokenSecret) {
    this.restTemplate = ProtectedResourceClientFactory.create(apiKey, apiSecret, accessToken, accessTokenSecret);
}]]>			</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				An OAuth2 example:
				<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public FacebookTemplate(String accessToken) {
    this.restTemplate = ProtectedResourceClientFactory.draft10(accessToken);
}]]>
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				Once the REST client has been configured as shown above, you simply use it to implement your various API bindings.
				The existing Spring Social client modules all invoke their RestTemplate instances in a standard manner:
				<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterProfile getUserProfile() {
    return restTemplate.getForObject(buildUri("account/verify_credentials.json"), TwitterProfile.class);
}]]>
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				A note on RestTemplate usage: we do favor the RestTemplate methods that accept a URI object instead of a uri String.
				This ensures we always properly encode client data submitted in URI query parameters, such as screen_name below:
				<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterProfile getUserProfile(String screenName) {
    return restTemplate.getForObject(buildUri("users/show.json", Collections.singletonMap("screen_name", screenName)), TwitterProfile.class);
}]]>
				</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				For complete implementation examples, consult the existing API bindings included in Spring Social.
				spring-social-twitter and spring-social-facebook provide particularly good references.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="service-provider-implementing-api-new-testing">
			<title>Testing a new Java API binding</title>
		</section>				
		<section id="service-provider-implementing-api-existing-integrating">
			<title>Integrating an existing Java API binding</title>
		</section>		
	</section>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing-oauth2">
		<title>OAuth2 Service Providers</title>
		<para>
			To implement an OAuth2-based ServiceProvider, first extend AbstractOAuth2ServiceProvider.
			Parameterize &lt;S&gt; to be the Java Binding to the ServiceProvider API.
			Define a single constructor that accepts an clientId and clientSecret,
			Finally, implement getServiceApi(String) to return a new API instance.
		</para>
		<para>
			See FacebookServiceProvider as an example of an OAuth2-based ServiceProvider:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public final class FacebookServiceProvider extends AbstractOAuth2ServiceProvider<FacebookApi> {

    public FacebookServiceProvider(String clientId, String clientSecret) {
        super(new OAuth2Template(clientId, clientSecret,
            "https://graph.facebook.com/oauth/authorize", 
            "https://graph.facebook.com/oauth/access_token"));
    }

    public FacebookApi getServiceApi(String accessToken) {
        return new FacebookTemplate(accessToken);
    }

}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			In the constructor, you should call super, passing up the configured OAuth2Template, which implements OAuth2Operations.
			The OAuth2Template will handle the "OAuth dance" with the provider, and should be configured with the provided clientId and clientSecret, along with the provider-specific authorizeUrl and accessTokenUrl.
		</para>
		<para>
			In getServiceApi(String), you should construct your Service API implementation, passing it the access token needed to make requests for protected resources.
			Inside the API implementation, we generally recommend using RestTemplate to make the HTTP calls and add the required Authorization header:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public FacebookTemplate(String accessToken) {
    // creates a RestTemplate that adds the OAuth2-draft10 Authorization header to each request before it is executed
    restTemplate = ProtectedResourceClientFactory.draft10(accessToken);
}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			An example API call with RestTemplate is shown below:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public FacebookProfile getUserProfile(String facebookId) {
    return new FacebookProfile(restTemplate.getForObject("https://graph.facebook.com/{facebookId}", Map.class, facebookId));
}]]>
		</programlisting>
	</section>
	<section id="service-providers-implementing-oauth1">
		<title>OAuth1 Service Providers</title>
		<para>
			To implement an OAuth1-based ServiceProvider, first extend AbstractOAuth1ServiceProvider.
			Parameterize &lt;S&gt; to be the Java Binding to the ServiceProvider API.
			Define a single constructor that accepts a consumerKey and consumerSecret.
			Finally, implement getServiceApi(String, String) to return a new API instance.
		</para>
		<para>
			See TwitterServiceProvider as an example of an OAuth1-based ServiceProvider:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public final class TwitterServiceProvider extends AbstractOAuth1ServiceProvider<TwitterApi> {

    public TwitterServiceProvider(String consumerKey, String consumerSecret) {
        super(consumerKey, consumerSecret,  new OAuth1Template(consumerKey, consumerSecret, 
                "https://twitter.com/oauth/request_token",
                "https://twitter.com/oauth/authorize",
                "https://twitter.com/oauth/access_token"));
    }

    public TwitterApi getServiceApi(String accessToken, String secret) {
        return new TwitterTemplate(getConsumerKey(), getConsumerSecret(), accessToken, secret);
    }

}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			In the constructor, you should call super, passing up the the consumerKey, secret, and configured OAuth1Template.
			The OAuth1Template will handle the "OAuth dance" with the provider.
			It should be configured with the provided consumerKey and consumerSecret, along with the provider-specific requestTokenUrl, authorizeUrl, and accessTokenUrl.
		</para>			
		<para>
			In getServiceApi(String, String), you should construct your Service API implementation, passing it the four tokens needed to make requests for protected resources.
			Inside the API implementation, we generally recommend using RestTemplate to make the HTTP calls and add the required Authorization header:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterTemplate(String consumerKey, String consumerSecret, String accessToken, String accessTokenSecret) {
    // creates a RestTemplate that adds the OAuth1 Authorization header to each request before it is executed
    restTemplate = ProtectedResourceClientFactory.create(consumerKey, consumerSecret, accessToken, accessTokenSecret);
}]]>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			An example API call with RestTemplate is shown below:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public TwitterProfile getUserProfile(String screenName) {
    return new TwitterProfile(restTemplate.getForObject("https://api.twitter.com/1/users/show.json?screen_name={screenName}", Map.class, screenName));
}]]>
		</programlisting>									
	</section>
</chapter>