<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="serviceprovider"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Service Provider Framework</title>

  <section xml:id="section_serviceproviderconfig">
      <title>Configuring Service Providers</title>
      
      <para>You can configure a service provider in the Spring application context using Spring Social's Spring configuration namespace:</para>
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans" 
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:social="http://www.springframework.org/schema/spring-social"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/spring-social 
             http://www.springframework.org/schema/social/spring-social-1.0.xsd
        http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans 
             http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd">
        
    ...
</beans>]]></programlisting>

      <para>The <code><![CDATA[<social:service-provider>]]></code> element can be used to configure any service provider in Spring. For example, to configure a Twitter provider:</para>
      
<programlisting><![CDATA[<social:service-provider id="twitter"
    consumer-key="twitter_key"
    consumer-secret="twitter_secret"
    display-name="Twitter"
    class="org.springframework.social.twitter.provider.TwitterServiceProvider"
    request-token-url="https://twitter.com/oauth/request_token" 
    authorization-url="https://twitter.com/oauth/authorize?oauth_token={requestToken}"
    access-token-url="https://twitter.com/oauth/access_token" />]]></programlisting>

      <para>The <code>consumer-key</code> and <code>consumer-secret</code> attributes specify the key and secret values assigned to your application when you registered it with the provider.</para>
      
      <para>The <code>display-name</code> attribute sets a name that describes the provider in user-friendly terms when referring to the provider in the application's user-interface. This is an optional parameter; if left blank, it will default to the value of the <code>id</code> attribute with the first character capitalized.</para>
      
      <para>The <code>request-token-url</code>, <code>authorization-url</code>, and <code>access-token-url</code> attributes set the URLs that Spring should use when coordinating authorization with the provider. The <code>request-token-url</code> is optional; if left blank, the provider is assumed to be an OAuth 2 provider.</para>
      
      <para>The <code>class</code> attribute specifies the fully-qualified name of the provider implementation. A service provider implementation should implement the <interfacename>ServiceProvider</interfacename> interface or extend either <classname>AbstractServiceProvider</classname>, <classname>AbstractOAuth1ServiceProvider</classname>, or <classname>AbstractOAuth2ServiceProvider</classname>.</para>
        
      <para>To make things simpler, the Spring Social namespace also offers a handful of configuration elements for the service providers for which Spring Social provides implementations (currently Twitter, Facebook, Gowalla, LinkedIn, and TripIt). For example, to configure a Twitter service provider:</para>
      
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<social:twitter-provider consumer-key="twitter_key" 
    consumer-secret="twitter_secret" />]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>Similarly, a Facebook service provider can be configured like this:</para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<social:facebook-provider consumer-key="facebook_key" 
    consumer-secret="facebook_secret" app-id="1234" />]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>Note that the Facebook service provider also takes an <code>app-id</code> attribute. Applications registered with Facebook are assigned an application ID along with the consumer key and secret that may be used by some parts of Facebook's API (such as the "Like" button).</para>
        
        <para>For a Gowalla service provider, the following XML may be used:</para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<social:gowalla-provider consumer-key="gowalla_key" 
    consumer-secret="gowalla_secret" />]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>Or for a TripIt service provider:</para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<social:tripit-provider consumer-key="tripit_key" 
    consumer-secret="tripit_secret" />]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>Finally, a LinkedIn service provider may be configured as follows:</para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<social:linkedin-provider consumer-key="linkedin_key" 
    consumer-secret="linkedin_secret" />]]></programlisting>
</section>
<section xml:id="section_knownserviceproviderconfig">
        <title>Configuring service providers in RDBMS</title>
        
        <para>Configuring service providers in Spring configuration is straightforward and very convenient. However, should you need to edit any of the service provider details, you would need to edit the Spring configuration and redeploy your application.</para>
        
        <para>One reason that you may need to edit your service provider details is if you reset your client key and secret. Let's say that those values fell into the wrong hands and some other application out there is posing as your application. Most OAuth providers make it easy to assign a new key/secret pair to applications, voiding the previous pair. But if your service provider is configured in Spring configuration, that means you'll need to make the changes, rebuild your application and then redeploy it.</para>
        
        <para>Optionally, you may choose to configure your service providers externally in a relational database. Spring Social's <classname>JdbcServiceProviderFactory</classname> can create service providers from configuration details stored in RDBMS.</para>
            
        <para>First, you must have a <code>ServiceProvider</code> table in your database. The following DDL creates a table suitable for use with <classname>JdbcServiceProviderFactory</classname>:</para> 

        <programlisting><![CDATA[create table ServiceProvider (name varchar,
    displayName varchar not null,
    implementation varchar not null,
    apiKey varchar not null,					
    secret varchar,
    appId bigint,
    requestTokenUrl varchar,
    authorizeUrl varchar,
    accessTokenUrl varchar,
    primary key (name));]]></programlisting>

        <para>With the <code>ServiceProvider</code> table in place, you may insert rows to represent each of the service providers your application will interact with. For example, you may insert a row for a Twitter service provider:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[insert into ServiceProvider (name, displayName, implementation, apiKey, secret, requestTokenUrl, authorizeUrl, 
      accessTokenUrl) values 
   ('twitter', 'Twitter', 'org.springframework.social.twitter.provider.TwitterServiceProvider', 
      'twitter_key', 'twitter_secret', 'https://twitter.com/oauth/request_token',
      'https://twitter.com/oauth/authorize?oauth_token={requestToken}',      
      'https://twitter.com/oauth/access_token');]]></programlisting>

        <para>Next, configure <classname>JdbcServiceProviderFactory</classname> in Spring:</para> 
        
    	<programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="serviceProviderFactory" class="org.springframework.social.provider.jdbc.JdbcServiceProviderFactory">
    <constructor-arg ref="jdbcTemplate" />
	<constructor-arg ref="stringEncryptor" />
</bean>]]></programlisting>

        <para>The constructor takes two arguments. The first is a reference to a <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> through which <classname>JdbcServiceProviderFactory</classname> will access the <code>ServiceProvider</code> table. The second is a reference to an implementation of <interfacename>StringEncryptor</interfacename> that will be used to encrypt/decrypt consumer keys and secrets as they're stored/retrieved from the <code>ServiceProvider</code> table.</para>
        
        <para>To simplify configuration of a <classname>JdbcServiceProviderFactory</classname>, the Spring Social configuration namespace also offers a <code><![CDATA[<social:jdbc-service-provider-factory>]]></code> element that can be used instead of the explicit bean declaration:</para>

    	<programlisting><![CDATA[<social:jdbc-service-provider-factory jdbc-template="jdbcTemplate" />]]></programlisting>
    	
    	<para>Here, the <code>jdbc-template</code> attribute refers to a <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> bean. Optionally, a <code>string-encryptor</code> attribute may refer to a <interfacename>StringEncryptor</interfacename> bean. However, if <code>string-encryptor</code> is not specified, it will default to a no-op implementation that does no encryption on the key/secret pairs.</para>
    	
        <para>Finally, use <classname>JdbcServiceProviderFactory</classname>'s <methodname>getServiceProvider()</methodname> method to declare the service provider beans themselves:</para>
    	
    	<programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="twitterProvider" factory-bean="serviceProviderFactory" factory-method="getServiceProvider">
	<constructor-arg value="twitter" />
</bean>]]></programlisting>    	
  </section>
</chapter>
